<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>wingS Whitepaper</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>wingS is a Java servlet based toolkit which presents a high level
    windowing API to the user. Applications created with wingS can then be
    deployed in a standard java servlet container to present a web based
    interface. Where possible interfaces and concepts are reused from the Java
    Swing API to minimise the learning curve. A programmer with basic Java
    knowledge should be able to write their own applications in wingS after a
    few hours familiarisation.</para>

    <para>The wingS framework takes care of the low level infrastructure
    needed to manage a Java servlet session, relieving the need to do any
    special state management. The framework also handles the rendering of the
    user interface in HTML, and the mapping of HTTP requests into high level
    events. Thus, apart from being aware of the general constraints imposed by
    HTTP/HTML, the programmer does not need to be concerned with the messy
    details of HTML formatting. Instead they deal with a high level windowing
    API with methods to open windows, layout components, and receive component
    events. This is in direct contrast to the majority of technologies being
    used to create web applications which require direct HTML-level formatting
    at some point.</para>

    <para>This clean architecture of wingS makes it suitable for the
    construction of complex, transactional applications. This is not to say
    that it cannot be used for simple applications, it has a small footprint
    and an easy learning curve, so is suitable for any type of web
    application. However the ability to correctly structure and layer your
    code will be most beneficial in large applications, where more typical
    scripting approaches collapse due to the poor structure dictated by the
    scripting technology.</para>

    <para>Apart from requiring a Java servlet container to execute, wingS is
    non-invasive and imposes no particular technical constraints. The display
    is always browser based and hence "thin-client", however you can implement
    many different architectures such as:<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Monolithic "fat client", just code it all as in-process
          java</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>J2EE application by using other standard J2EE
          facilities</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Classic multi-tier "thin client" by interfacing with a server
          middle-tier using the technology of your choice (SOAP, CORBA, RMI).
          Java natively offers plenty of choices</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>The server-side of a wingS application is inherently cross-platform
    being pure Java. On the web browser side wingS tries to be as inclusive as
    possible by adhering to W3C standards, and not requiring any special
    client-side plug-in. Reliance on JavaScript, the main source of browser
    incompatibility, is minimised. More adventurous users can customise the
    display rendering if required, using internal APIs, and work is on-going
    to better modularise these aspects of the toolkit.</para>

    <para>wingS applications have been deployed for several years in a variety
    of industries. The code is stable and mature.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Why Choose wingS?</title>

    <para>A summary of reasons you might consider wingS for your next project
    follows.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Clean Architecture</emphasis></para>

    <para>The majority of the API is in Java and presents a high-level
    interface using familiar concepts such as windows, widgets, and events.
    Thus you can structure your code in the way you want, rather than the way
    the technology forces you to. A portion of the toolkit uses cascading
    style sheets and a small amount of JavaScript. You are unlikely to be
    interested in this unless you intend customising the look and feel.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Open Architecture</emphasis></para>

    <para>Use of Java allows a cross platform "back-end", and reliance on
    basic web standards allows a cross-browser "front-end". No special
    plug-ins are required.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Open Licence</emphasis></para>

    <para>wingS is licenced using the GNU "LESSER GENERAL PUBLIC LICENSE"
    (LGPL) which means you can freely modify the source code, as well as
    safely use it for your own proprietary development.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Stable and Robust</emphasis></para>

    <para>wingS has been in use in commercial production environments for
    several years. These include vertical domains such as retail,
    manufacturing, logistics, financial services and local government.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Secure</emphasis></para>

    <para>Since wingS is a pure Java Servlet toolkit, deployment is very
    clean, this normally being a matter of copying over a few jar files, or a
    war file. This makes it harder to reverse engineer the application from
    outside a firewall, unlike solutions which rely heavily on scripting.
    Additionally the way that state management is implemented means that an
    application that needs to be transactional, will behave so. It is not
    possible to bookmark an intermediate point in an application's execution,
    and then later replay from this point. HTTP parameters are posted, rather
    than URL encoded. If you combine this with a standard SSL connection an
    application will be very hard to compromise.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Efficient</emphasis></para>

    <para>Use of programmatically generated HTML tends to result in HTML pages
    that are more efficient to download (requiring fewer round trips to the
    server) than pages produced by many HTML editors. wingS applications
    function well over a low bandwidth connection. The toolkit itself is
    moderately sized and has a modest memory footprint bt the standards of
    typical Java applications.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Scalable</emphasis></para>

    <para>Nothing in the wingS toolkit prevents you writing applications that
    can "scale out" to many concurrent users. The scalability limits are
    likely to depend on the other technologies you use in your
    application.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Easily Integrated</emphasis></para>

    <para>wingS uses standard Java Servlet sessions, so if you need to
    integrate other front-end technologies you can still access the normal
    Java Servlet API and access data bound to the same session. This should
    allow its use as part of a larger portal if required.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Deployed User Base</title>

    <para>Here's a list of companies volunteering to share with you what they
    have developed.</para>

    <table>
      <title>wingS Applications</title>

      <tgroup align="left" cols="2">
        <colspec colwidth="1.5*" />

        <colspec colwidth="1*" />

        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry align="center">Application</entry>

            <entry align="center">Company</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry valign="top">Financial management application for marketing
            programs in EMEA</entry>

            <entry morerows="2"><ulink
            url="http://www.exxcellent.de">eXXcellent solutions
            gmbH</ulink></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Research system for electrical wires, connectors and
            components in the automotive area</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Project and Resource management application</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>eCommerce solution, (B2B, B2C)</entry>

            <entry morerows="3"><ulink url="http://www.mercatis.de">mercatis
            information systems GmbH</ulink></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Corporate LDAP management application</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><ulink url="http://www.innovationsregion-ulm.de">Web
            directory</ulink></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Warehouse dispatcher software, PDA-based (wireless)</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Retail investment management performance reporting
            (intranet and extranet). Used by a group company of Close Brothers
            Group PLC, a FTSE250 company.</entry>

            <entry><ulink url="http://www.scinapps.com">Scinapps
            Ltd</ulink></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>Please contact the project, if you want to be added.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Technology Comparison</title>

    <section>
      <title>Comparision with JSF</title>

      <para>Comparison of wingS with Java Server Faces (JSF), and to a lesser
      extent Java Server Pages (JSP).</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Reasons to Choose JSF</emphasis></para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>It is backed by Sun.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Reason to Choose
      wingS</emphasis><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>You want to program in a single high level language. JSF
            spreads the application logic across multiple technologies - pure
            Java, tag-libraries, XML based action configuration and JSP
            pages.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>You don't want to learn a new syntax for writing HTML (via
            the JSF tag-libraries), or for binding the tag-library directives
            to Java code.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>You want more insulation from the low level details of HTML
            rendering</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>You prefer compile time errors to debugging runtime errors.
            The decoupled structure of the various modules of JSF creates a
            heavy burden of runtime testing.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>JSF requires extra state management on your part</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Your view layout is more complex, or more dynamic, than can
            be easily represented using a "static" JSF file
            specification.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Your application logic is more complex than can be easily
            handled using the simple navigation specification mechanism of
            "action files"</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>All debugging can be handled within java code</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>You are already familiar with the Java Swing API and related
            concepts</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">JSP Comments</emphasis></para>

      <para>JSF was conceived to address the severe shortcomings of JSP.
      However by taking this as a starting point it inherits most of the
      negative aspects of programming with JSP. Most of the disadvantages
      quoted above apply equally to JSP. The currently author once spent two
      months trying to create a simple JSP based application, using
      tag-libraries and XSLT processing to format the output. The end result
      was entirely unsatisfactory, and was replaced by a wingS application in
      a week.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Comparison with Scripting</title>

      <para>The comments here apply to general scripting solutions. This
      includes Perl-CGI, Python, ASP or ASP.Net. (Strangely Microsoft did not
      take the opportunity with .Net to provide a high level web API to a web
      interface. Instead they enhanced ASP (Web Forms), leaving many of the
      disadvantages, created a new pure windows client library, and require
      yet another technology for mobile devices).</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Reasons to Choose
      Scripting</emphasis><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Quick solution for small applications</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Intermediate technology level for less technical
            implementors</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Reasons to Choose
      wingS</emphasis><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Single technology</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>No embedding and data escaping issues</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Better encapsulation and scoping of modules</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Compile-time checking instead of runtime checking</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Scripting requires major cut and paste of HTML
            templates</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>HTML coding is low-level and too device / browser
            specific</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Scripting state management solutions tend to be
            clumsy</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Integration of script with other application code can be
            tricky. Database bindings are usually available, but if more data
            processing is required, this is hard to add.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>No special session state management</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Standard Compiance</title>

    <para>wingS is based on and compiled with Sun's Servlet API version 2.2.
    It uses Jakarta Commons Logging, Regexp, and HTTPClient for record/replay
    of session, as well as bsh-core. There are no other dependecies.</para>

    <para>Due to this non-invasive nature wingS is relatively light-weight and
    can easily be used in combination with other Servlet-based
    technologies.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Principles for Future Development</title>

    <para>The wingS team recognizes and subscribes to the following
    principles:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Swing API and behaviour - adhere to as close as possible &amp;
        sensible</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>W3C standards</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Support old JRE versions (currently JDK1.2), do not make latest
        JRE a requirement</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Monitor and embrace new developements in the web application
        arena </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</article>